what's the best way to stay healthy in
the face of so much conflicting
nutrition information well ideally you
would go to the source the gold standard
the peer-reviewed medical literature and
read through the stacks of the latest
medical journals but who's got time for
that I do welcome to the nutrition facts
podcast I'm your host Dr Michael Greger
today we'll run the gamut of topics from
whether or not those with genetic
markers for breast cancer should eat soy
the importance of getting enough vitamin
D and why some of us are overly
sensitive to garlic and onion let's see
what questions you have for me today
here's one from nanabuga
says is there any benefits aspirin has
to offer if you must take other
medications that might cause blood clots
well I mean ideally you would treat the
cause of whatever disease condition
um that made you have to take drugs that
cause blood clots and so then you
wouldn't have to be on those drugs but
taking aspirin for primary prevention uh
trying to for example prevent a heart
attack in the first place
um is not according to the uspsdf the
United States promoting a service task
force not recommended as the risks which
include major bleeding
um outweigh the benefits that however
changes for in certain circumstances for
secondary prevention so for example
we've already had a heart attack on
you're at such high risk of having a
second heart attack in that case
um the the the pros and cons May shift
in the other direction let's see who's
next Cheryl says help breast cancer my
family should I not eat tofu any soy
like yogurt or milk fantastic question
um so first of all only about
um two percent of breast cancers
actually
Fallen families you know those so-called
bracket genes I'm 98 of breast cancer
um is uh what we're exposed to
um and so just because it appears to to
come down the family it may just be
because there's similar Lifestyles diets
and Lifestyles um run in families as
well
um and so that's fantastic news and of
course even if you do have those
broccoli mutations or I have mutations
that put you at high risk well I mean
that's just you know the genetics loads
the gun lifestyle pulls the trigger
regardless of what kind of genetic cards
we've been dealt with we can reshuffle
that deck with diet and one of the ways
we can do that is by going out of our
way
to eat soy Foods
um so there's now been a half a dozen
studies now that have followed thousands
of breast cancer survivors and those who
ate soy have significantly put them all
all those studies together have
significantly lower risk of breast
cancer recurrence meaning significantly
lower risk of breast cancer coming back
and
um significantly improve survival
um so live longer than those breast
cancer survivors that who don't eat soy
um even better would be to eat breast to
eat soy Foods particularly in the
Adolescent years to decrease the risk of
uh of breast cancer later in life
between 30 and 50 percent lower risk
associated
um uh breast cancer is associated with
eating soy particularly at a younger age
um and so would encourage people to
include soy Foods some healthier than
others
um so a whole soy food would be ideal
something like edamame the immature
green soybeans in a pod fun tasty snack
in fact one of my favorite snacks
um as opposed to something like the the
uh soy yogurt which typically has a lot
of sugar added or soy milk
um which has those isoflavones those
those uh phytoestrogens that are so
beneficial but you know you're missing
the fiber you're missing um a lot of the
other um goodies that are in whole
soybeans so that would be the preferable
route
okay next one is Angelic asking does
black human have to be ground to uh get
the best absorption
um the uh the I think most of the
studies
um were using ground
um on black cumin seeds and uh so uh we
know from experiments with like uh flax
seeds for example that you really do
need to grind them to get the beneficial
effects otherwise they just pass through
you
um unless you chew really really well
but you know black cumin seeds are so
tiny that you really probably gonna miss
a few so yes ground black human is the
way to go for all its Associated
benefits
okay next up Laura says going on a lung
transplant list due to hypersensitivity
pneumonitis oh I'm so sorry to hear that
in years of the diet I should focus on
currently losing weight
um so
um uh I mean if you're overweight and
certainly that could help prep you
um for surgery
um uh so my advice in this circumstance
is really just
um uh you know all the typical healthy
advice but just to the nth degree right
so instead of like let's get a little
let's make sure you exercise you really
want to maximize your exercise regimen
maximize smoking cessation maximize
eating healthy daily dozen all the way
um to really get your body prepped for
the kind of trauma that is any surgery
and something called like lung
transplant is certainly major surgery
now after surgery
um increasing protein intake can help um
with healing
um but before surgery it was just a
matter of eating
um you know the recommended pointed
grams for healthy government body weight
okay next up oh no Nona is back saying
can I eat 20 sheets of nori uh see we
today
um I'm so glad that you love healthy
foods
um so uh two sheets has about 150 uh
micrograms so 10 would have 1500. what's
the maximum upper daily limit let me
look that quick my um upper daily limit
iodine let's check it out oh it is 1100
micrograms a day okay so that's too much
so uh let's stick let's let's let's
let's take a few sheets away let's go
what 16 is that gonna be anyway yeah so
I know they're delicious I snack on them
myself but two sheets today uh should
get you the recommended 150 micrograms
you need
um so uh let's not do 20 the risk of
excess iodine intake caused something
called hyperthyroidism overactive
thyroid glands which you want to avoid
okay next up Emily says hello anything
recommend for Oh Long covered fatigue oh
and one kidney since donating oh you are
so sweet
um I hope your mom is doing okay
um so um so anyone with one kidney needs
to eat a very uh extraordinarily kidney
healthy diet what is that that's a low
sodium Whole Food plant-based diet
um plant protein
um and not excess protein
um and I've got a bunch of videos on
both preventing and treating
um kidney failure and so that's that's
for that piece
and then what do we have for long covet
so we know uh you know from this massive
Harvard study 600 000 people that those
would be more whole plan foods and Less
meat eggs dairy and junk
um are not only significantly less
likely to get covered in the first place
but if they do get covered significantly
uh less likelihood of suffering a severe
course not to mention all the
comorbidities right what increases one's
risk of a serious coveted case you know
obesity diabetes high blood pressure
heart disease Etc all of which can be
prevented arrested and reversed with a
healthy enough plant-based diet but what
about long coven we simply don't know
the studies haven't been done to find
out what kind of Lifestyle
um uh approaches can be used to deal
with long coveted symptoms yeah you know
if it is an inflammatory component one
would presume an anti-inflammatory diet
which is synonymous with the whole food
plant-based diet would help but you
haven't hasn't been put to the test I
myself suffered a long coveted symptom
of this sciatic amount of neuropathy
um for about a month and thankfully it
went away but definitely
was I couldn't be on my treadmill I
remember remember I was given my q a one
month though treadmill again I can
recommend just taking good care of
yourself unfortunately we don't have
data either way for any diet any
lifestyle intervention or really any
drug intervention at this point I mean
this you were just so early with
understanding long coven that
unfortunately
um all I can do is you know this generic
healthy advice
um you know getting enough sleep etc etc
now on his back all right can you be
sensitive can you be sensitive to garlic
and onion uh why feel bloated every day
well there are um you know fodmaps
um there are these prebiotics uh found
in allium family vegetables like garlic
onion chives shallots Etc that are super
healthy for your gut bugs
um but if you have dysbiosis if you have
the wrong gut bugs then you can foster
the growth of the wrong kind
um and so if you're really sensitive
um uh then uh um then you can try
cutting down see if that helps but I
would
um start slowly adding them back to your
diet
um based on your tolerance
um so you can build up the uh the the
the good bugs because you want to get to
the point where you can include these
super healthy foods into your diet okay
Heather says can I touch more on
supplements beyond the daily dose and I
bring a drink of protein shake should I
be wary of these or are there certain
ones I'd recommend the one I use they'll
pump base uh from a company named vega
I'm 53 taking multivitamin okay you do
not need to eat a protein shake
all right we should get all our
macronutrients our protein our carbs and
fat from Whole plant Foods right
um and so it's not it's like we don't
get our carbs in form of sugar
um we don't get our fat in the forms of
oil and we don't get our protein in the
form of powder which is you know what
these protein shakes are
um and uh and so you know it's it's so
simple to get the recommended
um intake 0.8 grams per half the
kilogram body weight of protein eating
whole healthy foods and some of the
healthiest foods like legumes beans
split peas chickpeas lentils that's what
I would uh recommend you eat instead
um so I've got videos about
multivitamins and there's some people
like you know alcoholics
um uh um during pregnancy there's some
there's some
um situations in which
um taking multivitamin is a good idea
and I talk about um circumstances in my
videos but for uh most people
um it is uh unnecessary of course what
you should be the supplement I do
recommend
is vitamin B12 critically important for
anyone eating a healthy diet getting a
regular reliable source of vitamin B12
and if you're not getting enough Sun
um and so during the winter months if
you're getting inadequate Sunshine uh
you may want to supplement uh with 2000
international units of vitamin D3
okay what does Science Show Oh mushrooms
like ashwagandha ashwagandha is not a
mushroom it's a root
um and other types of mushrooms that
claim to be supportive for good mood
relaxation
um actually I just um I uh talk about
ashwagandha in my sex chapter in how not
to age let's look it up preserving your
sex life that's my uh that's the chapter
I remember I talked about all the
various Roots Maca ashwagandha what's
the other one ginseng I think yeah all
right let's see what we got ashuganda
revered herb of the ayurvedic system of
medicine which is the Indian tradition
of medicine its name comes from ashwa
meaning horse and gone to meaning smell
because the roots evidently possess the
distinctive smell of a wet horse I did
not know that before writing this book
um ashwagandha has used this household
remedy in India where it's considered a
rasayana
I know probably mispronouncing that a
rejuvenator or a tonic for thousands of
years earning the nickname Indian
ginseng okay so does it actually help
let's find out rodents thrown to the
deep end the swim twice as long before
sinking 12 hours versus six hours after
being fed ashwagandha
um and uh so what about people benefits
for physical performance including
increases in aerobic fitness have been
found in people too that's exciting one
study demonstrate evidence of cognitive
benefit as well it's Latin
nameifora points to another use
somnifera means sleep inducer a
meta-analysis of five randomized
controlled Trials of ashwagandha
extracts found a small but significant
effect on overall sleep what about
which is what this chapter is about what
about ashwagandha and female sexual
function women ages 21 through 50 were
randomized to two months of the
estimated equivalent of three grams of
ashwagandha root powder so it'll be
about a teaspoon a day did not have an
increase in sexual desire but did show
improvements over Placebo in arousal
lubrication orgasm and satisfaction
translating to an initial successful
sexual encounter by the end of the study
and so what how many two months one per
two months all right okay what are the
downsides
ashwagandha belongs to the nightshade
family which includes some shady
characters like tobacco and well deadly
nightshade there have been rare cases of
ashwagandha linked liver toxicity uh
though commercial herbal supplements are
often mislabeled so it's hard to
definitively attribute certain cases
right so just because someone has liver
toxicity and they're taking something
that says ashwagandha who knows what's
actually in the bottle however there
have been several liver injury cases in
which supplements have been tested and
found to be contaminant free so it was
actually ashwagandha suggesting that
ashwagandha induced liver toxicity is a
real phenomenon even though it's rare
um but what should we expect from a
plant known by another nickname poison
gooseberry
so I don't recommend you take it
sorry for the long explanation but not
what a nice little sneak preview from a
little blurb uh from now not the age
okay anyway
um often read that cancer feeds off
sugar
asks Kerala
um some people say whole food is like
sugar for cancer cells do you recommend
cutting down a fruit for healthy people
is there's too much fruit today that's
fantastic questions so I actually did a
video uh talking
um on this very question
um uh cancer uh cancer like all cells
feeds off of sugar
um but cancer can feed off of fat too in
fact there's the the you know there's I
talk about the these these Ketone eating
um cancer
um cells they're just fast growing cells
so they eat whatever we're eating uh
fruit is packed with phytonutrients
actually cancer preventive the the
um the American Institute for cancer
research was kind of like the
kind of main body that talks about diet
and cancer recommends
um the same diet for cancer prevention
as for cancer treatment the same diet
that prevents cancer can be used to
treat it um to help treat it and what's
that cancer preventive diet it is a diet
centered around whole plant food
specifically relying out of the way to
include to increase fruit and vegetable
intake whole grains legumes Etc cut down
a meat
um and added sugars Etc so yes I would
cut down to add sugars added salt added
fat and stick to whole plant Foods
um oh Ramone 70 year old trying to avoid
BPH and cancer by eating pumpkin seed
pumpkin seeds and oysters once a month
what do I think about that all right
let's look at BPH we want to go back to
the that's not in the sex chapter that's
in the uh bowel bladder
chapter preserving your bowel and
bladder function do not talk about
oysters in the BBH uh chapter so
presumably there's no research either
way
um but let's look about pumpkin seeds
shall we flax seeds can be used to treat
BPH uh men given the equivalent of three
tablespoons of flaxseed today experience
relief comparable to uh that bomb uh to
that provided by a commonly prescribed
drug such as Flomax or pro-scar without
the drug side effects that's exciting
what about other seeds
um so I think I talked about flax seeds
and how not to die and so I just do the
quick little all right it works it works
as well as the drug let's move on to uh
see what other seeds pumpkin seeds uh
evidently known as a folk medicine
treatment for prostate disorders for
centuries petri dish can cut down the
growth of BPH prostate cells in half
that's good
um and we can reduce the size of rat
prostates but who cares unless you have
a pet rat or something what about people
here we go so a pumpkin seed oil and
oil-free pumpkin seed extract so both
the fat soluble non-fat soluble
supplements um have appeared to help
um one with comparable efficacy of the
drug terazosin
um others didn't do as prezos and or
tamelosin but also didn't cause drug
side effects with names like retrograde
ejaculation
um unfortunately none of the
head-to-head drug trials had Placebo
worm
um so be nice to see how well the
placebo does the supplement does against
Placebo and in an Ideal World we'd like
to see a third group who's just given
whole pumpkin seeds not like some
extract and boom group of German
researchers took up the mantle more than
a thousand men were randomized either
pumpkin seed extract a matching Placebo
or just a tablespoon a day of plain
pumpkin seeds let's see what happens
the study was funded by the drug company
that made the supplement right but the
supplement totally flopped reducing
symptoms no better than the placebo but
guess what pumpkin seeds themselves
worked someone appeared to reduce
symptoms but not better than Placebo but
the seeds did
um the placebo was actually quite
effective offering clinical significant
relief and 68 of men wow but the pumpkin
seeds did the same
um for uh 83 percent
um so that's exciting bottom line
researchers suggest quote pumpkin seed
could be recommended for BPH patients
with mild to moderate symptoms unquote
and the conclusion was echoed by the
European equivalent of the FDA pumpkin
seeds can be used for quote the relief
of lower urinary tract symptoms related
to enlarged prostate after more serious
conditions have been excluded by a
medical doctor unquote
so yeah I encourage you uh to take
pumpkin seeds and I got a whole bunch of
other things you can do
um I um I hope you enjoy that chapter
um uh what do I think about avoiding Sun
Expo do you think if we avoid Sun
explosion take vitamin D D3 supplements
we lose any other positive essential
benefits that the sun may offer
um well it's certainly true
um uh that that if you avoid sun
exposure you would avoid the benefits
but you also avoid the downsides likes
skin cancer as well as Skin aging I talk
a lot about Sun avoidance for skin aging
um uh and uh so
um but the critical benefit
um that we know of is vitamin D so we
can offset that um through
supplementation and the other benefits
like you know uh potentially the
infrared and stuff uh even though it
does cause skin aging
um might it have some other benefits I
talk about some really funky thing with
CoQ10 I have a video about that but
they're really more theoretical so we
just have theoretical benefits versus
actual very real risks and so that's why
I would encourage people to use some
protective behaviors
foreign
we would love it if you could share with
us your stories about Reinventing Your
Health through evidence-based nutrition
go to nutritionfacts.org testimonials we
may be able to share it on our social
media to help Inspire others to see any
graphs charts Graphics images or studies
mentioned here please go to the
nutrition facts podcast landing page
there you'll find all the detailed
information you need plus links to all
the sources we cite for each of these
topics for our Vital timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics you can
order the ebook audiobook or hard copy
of my latest book how to survive a
pandemic
for recipes check out my new how not to
diet cookbook it's beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes for delicious
and nutritious meals and of course all
the proceeds are received from the sales
of all my books go to charity
nutritionfacts.org is a non-profit
science-based Public Service where you
can sign up for free daily updates on
the latest in nutrition research via
bite-sized videos and articles
everything on the website is free
there's no ads no corporate sponsorship
no Kickbacks it's strictly
non-commercial not selling anything I
just put it up as a public service as a
labor of love as a tribute to my
grandmother whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition